I experienced my first coup d'état at the age of four.
عشت أول انقلاب ببلدي في سن الرابعة.
Because of the coup d'état,
وبسبب الانقلاب،
my family had to leave my native home of Ghana
اضطرت عائلتي لمغادرة موطني غانا
As luck would have it,
ولسوء الحظ، بعد 6 أشهر من وصولنا،
they too had a military coup.
حدث انقلاب عسكري مرة أخرى.
I vividly remember being woken up in the middle of the night
أتذكر جيدًا أننا استيقظنا بمنتصف الليل
and gathering the few belongings we could
وجمعنا ما استطعنا من الأمتعة القليلة
and walking for about two hours
ومشينا لحوالي ساعتين
to a safe house.
بحثا عن منزل آمن.
For a week, we slept under our beds
نِمْنَا لأسابيع تحت أسِرَّتِنَا
because we were worried that bullets might fly through the window.
لأننا كنا خائفين من رصاصٍ قد يعبر النافذة.
Then, at the age of eight,
وفي سن الثامنة،
we moved to Botswana.
انتقلنا إلى بوتسوانا.
This time, it was different.
هذه المرة، كان الأمر مختلفا.
There were no coups.
لم يكن هناك انقلابات.
Everything worked. Great education.
كل شيء على ما يرام. تعليم جيد.
They had such good infrastructure that even at the time they had
كانت لديهم بنية تحتية جيدة، بل كان لديهم
a fiber-optic telephone system,
وقتها أيضا نظام هاتفي بالألياف البصرية،
long before it had reached Western countries.
قبل وقت طويل من وصوله للبلدان الغربية.
The only thing they didn't have
الأمر الوحيد الذي لم يكن لديهم
is that they didn't have
هو أنه لم تكن لديهم
their own national television station,
قناة تلفزية وطنية،
and so I remember watching
لذا أتذكر أني كنت أشاهد
TV from neighboring South Africa,
قناةً تبث من الجارة جنوب أفريقيا،
and watching Nelson Mandela in jail
وأشاهد نيلسون مانديلا في السجن
being offered a chance to come out
وقد خُيِّرَ للخروج من السجن
if he would give up the apartheid struggle.
إن تخلى عن النضال ضد الفصل العنصري.
But he didn't. He refused to do that
لكنه لم يفعل. ورفض ذلك إلى أن حقق هدفه
of freeing South Africa from apartheid.
بتحرير جنوب أفريقيا من الفصل العنصري.
And I remember feeling how just one good leader
وأتذكر أني شعرت كيف أن قائد واحد جيد
could make such a big difference in Africa.
قادر على خلق فرق كبير كهذا بأفريقيا.
Then at the age of 12,
وفي سن الثانية عشرة،
my family sent me to high school in Zimbabwe.
أرسلتني أسرتي إلى الثانوية بزيمبابوي.
Initially, this too was amazing:
بداية، كان هذا وحده أمرا مدهشا:
growing economy, excellent infrastructure,
اقتصاد نامٍ وبنية تحتية ممتازة
and it seemed like it was a model
وكان يبدو كنموذج للاقتصاد النامي بأفريقيا.
I graduated from high school in Zimbabwe
تخرجت من الثانوية بزيمبابوي
and I went off to college.
وذهبت إلى الكلية.
Six years later, I returned to the country.
بعد 6 سنوات، عدت إلى الوطن.
Everything was different.
كل شيء تغير.
It had shattered into pieces.
كان مقسما إلى قطع.
Millions of people had emigrated,
نزح الملايين من الناس،
the economy was in a shambles,
كان الاقتصاد بفوضى عارمة،
and it seemed all of a sudden that 30 years
وبدا فجأة أن 30 سنة من النمو قد اندثرت.
How could a country go so bad so fast?
كيف يمكن أن تسوء أمور بلد بهذه السرعة؟
Most people would agree
معظم الناس سيوافقون
that it's all because of leadership.
على أن كل ذلك بسبب القيادة.
One man, President Robert Mugabe,
رجل واحد، الرئيس روبرت موغابي،
is almost single-handedly responsible
هو تقريبا المسؤول الوحيد عن تدمير البلد.
Now, all these experiences of living in different
كل هذه التجارب التي عشتها
parts of Africa growing up
بمختلف أرجاء أفريقيا قدمت لي أمرين.
The first is it made me fall in love with Africa.
أولهما، جعلتني أقع بحب أفريقيا.
Everywhere I went,
حيثما ذهبت، خَبِرْتُ الجمال الأخاذ لقارتنا
and saw the resilience and the spirit of our people,
وشَهِدْتُ لين وروح شعبنا،
and at the time, I realized that I wanted to dedicate
وأدركت حينها أني سأهب بقية حياتي
the rest of my life to making this continent great.
لجعل هذه القارة هي الأعظم.
But I also realized that making Africa great
كما أدركت بأن جَعْلَ أفريقيا عظيمة
would require addressing this issue of leadership.
سيتطلب منا مناقشة قضية القيادة.
You see, all these countries I lived in,
فكل تلك الدول التي عشت بها،
the coups d'état
كل الانقلابات والفساد الذي رأيته بغانا
contrasted with the wonderful examples I had seen
يتعارض والأمثلة الجميلة التي رأيتها
in Botswana and in South Africa of good leadership.
ببوتسوانا وجنوب أفريقيا تحت قيادة جيدة.
It made me realize that Africa would rise or fall
مما جعلني أدرك بأن أفريقيا ستنهض أو تسقط
because of the quality of our leaders.
بسبب نوعية قادتنا.
Now, one might think, of course,
قد يقول أحدهم، بالطبع،
leadership matters everywhere.
القيادة مهمة في كل مكان.
But if there's one thing you take away from my talk today, it is this:
لكن إن خرجتم بأمر ما من محادثتي هذه، فهو:
In Africa, more than anywhere else in the world,
في أفريقيا، أكثر من أي مكان بالعالم،
the difference that just one good leader can make
الفرق الذي قد يشكله قائد واحد جيد
is much greater than anywhere else, and here's why.
هو أكبر من أي مكان آخر، والسبب هو.
It's because in Africa, we have weak institutions,
أنه في أفريقيا، لدينا مؤسسات ضعيفة،
like the judiciary, the constitution,
كالسلطة القضائية والدستور
civil society and so forth.
والمجتمع المدني واللائحة طويلة.
So here's a general rule of thumb that I believe in:
إليكم الآن القاعدة التي أؤمن بها:
When societies have strong institutions,
عندما تمتلك المجتمعات مؤسسات قوية،
the difference that one good leader can make is limited,
فالفرق الذي يشكله القائد الجيد هو محدود،
but when you have weak institutions,
لكن عندما يكون لديكم مؤسسات ضعيفة،
then just one good leader
فإن قائد جيد واحد فقط
can make or break that country.
بإمكانه بناء أو هدم ذلك البلد.
Let me make it a bit more concrete.
دعوني أضرب لكم مثلا ملموسا.
You become the president of the United States.
تخيل أنك أصبحت رئيسا للولايات المتحدة.
You think, "Wow, I've arrived.
تقول لنفسك: "يا إلهي، لقد فعلتها.
I'm the most powerful man in the world."
أنا الآن أقوى رجل على الأرض."
So you decide, perhaps let me pass a law.
فتقول، ربما سيسمحون لي بتمرير هذا القانون.
All of a sudden, Congress taps you on the shoulder
فجأة، يمسكك الكونغرس من كتفك
and says, "No, no, no, no, no, you can't do that."
فيقول: "لا لا لا لا يمكنك فعل ذلك."
You say, "Let me try this way."
فتقول: "دعني أجرب هذا الطريق."
The Senate comes and says, "Uh-uh,
يأتي مجلس الشيوخ ويقول: "اه،
we don't think you can do that."
لا نظن أنه يمكنك فعل ذلك."
You say, perhaps, "Let me print some money.
فتقول، ربما: "سيسمحون لي بِسَك بعض العملة.
I think the economy needs a stimulus."
برأيي الاقتصاد بحاجة لبعض التحفيز."
The central bank governor will think you're crazy.
سيظن محافظ البنك المركزي
You might get impeached for that.
أنك مجنونا، وقد تعزل بسبب ذلك.
But if you become the president of Zimbabwe,
لكن إن أصبحت رئيس زيمبابوي،
and you say, "You know, I really like this job.
فتقول: "أتعلمون، أحببت بالفعل هذا العمل.
I think I'd like to stay in it forever." (Laughter)
أظن أني سأبقى فيه للأبد." (ضحك)
Well, you just can.
والحقيقة، بإمكانك فعل ذلك.
You decide you want to print money.
فتقرر أنك بحاجة لسك العملة.
You call the central bank governor and you say,
تتصل بمحافظ البنك المركزي وتخبره،
"Please double the money supply."
"أرجو أن تضاعف الكتلة النقدية."
He'll say, "Okay, yes, sir,
سيقول لك: "السمع والطاعة سيدي،
is there anything else I can do for you?"
هل من شيء آخر يمكنني فعله لسيادتكم؟"
This is the power that African leaders have,
هذه هي السلطة التي بين أيدي قادة أفريقيا،
and this is why they make the most difference
ولهذا السبب يشكلون معظم الفرق في القارة.
The good news is that
الخبر السار هو
the quality of leadership in Africa has been improving.
أن جودة القيادة بأفريقيا قد تحسنت.
We've had three generations of leaders, in my mind.
برأيي، لقد مر علينا 3 أجيال من القادة.
Generation one are those who appeared
الجيل الأول كانوا أولئك الذين ظهروا
in the '50s and '60s.
بين الخمسينيات والستينيات.
These are people like Kwame Nkrumah of Ghana
وكانوا من أمثال، كوامي نكروما من غانا
and Julius Nyerere of Tanzania.
وجوليوس نيريري في تنزانيا.
The legacy they left is that they brought independence to Africa.
والإرث الذي خلفوه هو تحريرهم لأفريقيا.
They freed us from colonialism,
حررونا من الاستعمار،
and let's give them credit for that.
لذا دعونا نعترف لهم بهذا الجميل.
They were followed by generation two.
بعدها تبعهم الجيل الثاني.
These are people that brought nothing
وهم اللذين لم يقدموا شيئا
but havoc to Africa.
لكنهم دمَّروا أفريقيا.
Think warfare, corruption, human rights abuses.
من حربٍ وفسادٍ وانتهاكٍ لحقوق الإنسان.
This is the stereotype of the typical African leader
إنها الصورة النمطية لقائد أفريقي نموذجي
that we typically think of:
وأول من يخطر ببالكم هو:
Mobutu Sese Seko from Zaire,
موبوتو سيسي سيكو من زائير،
Sani Abacha from Nigeria.
ساني أباتشا من نيجيريا.
The good news is that most of these leaders have moved on,
الخبر السار هو أن معظمهم قد ترك السلطة،
and they were replaced by generation three.
وحل محلهم الجيل الثالث.
These are people like the late Nelson Mandela
وهم من أمثال الراحل نيلسون مانديلا
and most of the leaders that we see in Africa today,
ومعظم القادة الأفارقة اللذين نراهم اليوم،
like Paul Kagame and so forth.
مثل بول كاغامي وغيره.
Now these leaders are by no means perfect,
قد لا يكون هؤلاء القادة مثاليين،
but the one thing they have done is that they have
لكن الأمر الوحيد الذي قاموا به هو
cleaned up much of the mess of generation two.
أنهم نظفوا الكثير من فوضى الجيل الثاني.
They've stopped the fighting,
فقد أوقفوا الحروب،
and I call them the stabilizer generation.
وأنا أسميهم جيل الاستقرار.
They're much more accountable to their people,
وأصبحوا أكثر مساءلة أمام شعوبهم،
they've improved macroeconomic policies,
وقد حسنوا سياسات الاقتصاد الكلي،
and we are seeing for the first time
ونلاحظ ولأول مرة
Africa's growing, and in fact it's the second fastest
نمو أفريقيا، والواقع أنها ثاني أسرع
growing economic region in the world.
منطقة من حيث النمو الاقتصادي بالعالم.
So these leaders are by no means perfect,
لذا قد لا يكون هؤلاء القادة مثاليين،
but they are by and large
لكنهم وبشكل عام أحسن القادة
the best leaders we've seen in the last 50 years.
الذين مروا علينا في 50 سنة الأخيرة.
So where to from here?
الذي أقصده من هذا الكلام؟
I believe that the next generation
أني أؤمن بأن الجيل القادم
to come after this, generation four,
بعد هذا، أي الجيل الرابع،
has a unique opportunity
لديه الفرصة الفريدة لتحويل القارة.
Specifically, they can do two things
وخاصةً، أنه بإمكانهم فِعْلُ أمرين
that previous generations have not done.
لم تقم به الأجيال السابقة.
The first thing they need to do
أولا عليهم خلق الازدهار بالقارة.
Why is prosperity so important?
ما هي أهمية الازدهار؟
Because none of the previous generations
لأنه لم يتمكن أي من الأجيال السابقة
have been able to tackle this issue of poverty.
من القضاء على مشكل الفقر.
Africa today
أفريقيا اليوم تملك أسرع نمو سكاني بالعالم،
but also is the poorest.
لكنها أيضا الأفقر.
and by 2050, it will have the largest workforce in the world.
أكبر من الصين، وفي 2050، في العالم.
One billion people will need jobs in Africa,
سيحتاج مليار أفريقي للعمل،
so if we don't grow our economies fast enough,
لذا إن لم تنمو اقتصاداتنا بالسرعة الكافية،
we're sitting on a ticking time bomb,
سنكون كالجالس على قنبلة موقوتة،
not just for Africa but for the entire world.
ليس فقط لأفريقيا بل للعالم جميعا.
Let me show you an example
دعوني أضرب لكم المثل
of one person who is living up to this legacy
بشخص أخذ على عاتقه مسؤولية
of creating prosperity: Laetitia.
خلق الازدهار: ليتيسيا.
Laetitia's a young woman from Kenya
هي شابة من كينيا
who at the age of 13 had to drop out of school
كان عليها ترك المدرسة في سن 13
because her family couldn't afford to pay fees for her.
لأن أسرتها عجزت عن دفع مصاريف تعليمها.
So she started her own business rearing rabbits,
فبدأت بمشروع لتربية الأرانب،
which happen to be a delicacy in this part of Kenya
والتي تعتبر طبقا ثمينا بمنطقتها.
This business did so well that within a year,
وقد نجح المشروع منذ السنة الأولى،
she was employing 15 women
حيث أصبحت تشغل 15 امرأة
and was able to generate enough income
وتمكنت من تحقيق ما يكفي من المداخيل
that she was able to send herself to school,
لترسل نفسها إلى المدرسة،
and through these women
ومن خلال تلك النسوة
fund another 65 children to go to school.
ساعدة 65 طفلا من الذهاب إلى المدرسة.
The profits that she generated,
واستخدمت الأرباح التي حققتها، لبناء مدرسة،
and today she educates
واليوم تساهم بتدريس 400 طفل من مجتمعها.
And she's just turned 18.
وقد بلغت للتو سن 18.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Another example is Erick Rajaonary.
المثال الثاني هو إيريك رجاونوري.
Erick comes from the island of Madagascar.
هو من جزيرة مدغشقر.
Now, Erick realized that agriculture
المهم، أدرك إيريك أن الفلاحة
would be the key to creating jobs
هي المفتاح لخلق فرص الشغل
in the rural areas of Madagascar,
بالمناطق القروية في مدغشقر،
but he also realized that fertilizer was a very
لكنه أدرك أيضا بأن الأسمدة كانت جد
expensive input for most farmers in Madagascar.
باهظة بالنسبة لجميع المزارعين هناك.
Madagascar has these very special bats
ويوجد بمدغشقر نوعا فريدا من الخفافيش
that produce these droppings
ينتج فضلات
that are very high in nutrients.
تحتوي على نسب عالية من المغذيات.
In 2006, Erick quit his job as a chartered accountant
في 2006، ترك إيريك عمله كمحاسب قانوني
and started a company to manufacture
وأنشأ شركة لتصنيع الأسمدة من فضلات الخفاش.
Today, Erick has built a business
اليوم، يملك إيريك مشروعا
that generates several million dollars of revenue,
يُدِرُّ عليه مداخيل بملايين من الدولارات،
and he employs 70 people full time
ويشغل 70 شخصا بدوام كامل
and another 800 people during the season
و800 آخرين بشكل موسمي
when the bats drop their droppings the most.
في فترة ارتفاع إنتاج الخفافيش للفضلات.
Now, what I like about this story
ما يعجبني بهذه القصص
is that it shows that opportunities to create prosperity
هو أن الفرص لخلق الازدهار
can be found almost anywhere.
بمكن إيجادها في أي مكان.
Erick is known as the Batman.
واليوم يُعْرَف إيريك بالرجل الخفاش.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And who would have thought that you would have
ومن كان ليعتقد بأنه يمكنكم
been able to build a multimillion-dollar business
إنشاء مشروع بملايين الدولارات
employing so many people just from bat poo?
يشغل العديد من الناس من فضلات الخفاش؟
The second thing that this generation needs to do
الأمر الثاني الذي يجب أن يقوم به هذا الجيل
is to create our institutions.
هو خلق مؤسساتنا الخاصة.
They need to build these institutions such that we
عليهم بناء تلك المؤسسات بحيث
are never held to ransom again
لا نبقى أبدا تحت سيطرة
by a few individuals like Robert Mugabe.
بضعة أشخاص مثل روبرت موغابي.
Now, all of this sounds great,
كل هذا يبدو رائعا،
but where are we going to get this generation four from?
من أين سنحصل على هذا الجيل الرابع؟
Do we just sit and hope that they emerge
هل علينا الجلوس والتأمل في أن يظهر
by chance, or that God gives them to us?
بالصدفة، أو أن ينعم به علينا الله؟
No, I don't think so.
لا، لا أظن ذلك.
It's too important an issue for us to leave it to chance.
إنه أمر أهم من أن نتركه للصدفة.
I believe that we need to create African institutions,
أعتقد بأننا بحاجة لخلق مؤسسات أفريقية،
home-grown, that will identify and develop
محلية، تعمل على تحديد وتطوير
these leaders in a systematic, practical way.
قادة الغد بطريقة منهجية وعملية.
We've been doing this for the last 10 years
وهذا ما نفعله منذ السنوات 10 الأخيرة
through the African Leadership Academy.
بواسطة الأكاديمية الأفريقية للقيادة.
Laetitia is one of our young leaders.
ليتيسيا هي واحدة من قادتنا الشباب.
Today, we have 700 of them that are being groomed
اليوم، نحن في طور إعداد 700 قائد
for the African continent,
للقارة الأفريقية،
and over the next 50 years,
وفي 50 سنة المقبلة، نتوقع إعداد 6000 قائد.
But one thing has been troubling me.
لكن هناك أمر واحد يزعجني.
We would get about 4,000 applications a year
سنتلقى حوالي 4,000 طلب التحاق بالسنة
for 100 young leaders that we could take
مقابل 100 قائد شاب يمكننا استقبالهم
into this academy,
في هذه الأكاديمية،
and so I saw the tremendous hunger that existed
وقد شاهدت التعطش المتزايد
for this leadership training that we're offering.
على التدريب الذي نقدمه لإعداد القادة.
But we couldn't satisfy it.
لكن لا يسعنا تلبية جميع الطلبات.
So today, I'm announcing for the first time in public
لذا أعلن اليوم ولأول مرة على الملأ
an extension to this vision for the African Leadership Academy.
توسع رؤية الأكاديمية الأفريقية للقيادة.
We're building 25 brand new universities in Africa
ببناء 25 جامعة جديدة في أفريقيا
that are going to cultivate this next generation
التي ستُنَمِّي ذلك الجيل القادم
of African leaders.
من القادة الأفارقة.
Each campus will have 10,000 leaders at a time
سيكون بكل حرم جامعي 10,000 قائد بنفس الوقت
so we'll be educating and developing
بحيث سندرس ونطور
250,000 leaders at any given time.
250,000 قائد في شتى المجالات.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Over the next 50 years, this institution
خلال 50 سنة المقبلة، ستخلق هذه المؤسسة
will create three million transformative leaders
3 ملايين قائد تحولي من أجل القارة.
My hope is that half of them
أرجو أن يصبح نصفهم رجال أعمال نحتاجهم،
who will create these jobs that we need,
سيخلقون فرص عمل نحتاجها،
and the other half
والنصف الآخر سينظم إلى الحكومة
and the nonprofit sector,
والقطاع الغير ربحي،
and they will build the institutions that we need.
وسيبنون المؤسسات التي نحتاجها.
But they won't just learn academics.
لكنهم لن يتلقوا الجانب النظري فقط.
They will also learn how to become leaders,
بل سيتعلمون أيضا كيف يصبحون قادة،
and they will develop their skills as entrepreneurs.
وسيطورون مهاراتهم كرجال أعمال.
So think of this as Africa's Ivy League,
تخيلوا رابطة اللبلاب الأفريقية،
but instead of getting admitted because of your SAT scores
لكن عوض قبولكم لاجتيازكم مباراة الولوج
or because of how much money you have
أو للأموال التي تمتلكونها أو لعائلتكم،
the main criteria for getting into this university
فإن المعيار الرئيسي لولوج هذه الجامعة
will be what is the potential that you have
سيكون هو، ما هي الإمكانات التي تملكون
for transforming Africa?
لتحويل أفريقيا؟
But what we're doing is just one group of institutions.
لكن ما نبنيه هو مجرد مجموعة مؤسسات.
We cannot transform Africa by ourselves.
لا يمكننا تحويل أفريقيا لوحدنا.
My hope
أملي هو
is that many, many other home-grown
أن تزهر مؤسسات أفريقية محلية أخرى كثيرة،
and these institutions will all come together
بحيث تأتي جميع تلك المؤسسات
with a common vision of developing
برؤية مشتركة لتطوير
this next generation of African leaders,
الجيل القادم من القادة الأفارقة،
generation four,
الجيل الرابع،
and they will teach them this common message:
وسَيُعَلِّمُونَهُم هذه الرسالة المشتركة:
create jobs, build our institutions.
خلق فرص الشغل وبناء مؤسساتنا.
Nelson Mandela once said,
قال نيلسون مانديلا مرة،
"Every now and then,
"في كل زمان وعصر،
a generation is called upon to be great.
هناك جيل مُطَالَبٌ أن يكون عظيما.
You can be that great generation."
كونوا أنتم ذاك الجيل العظيم."
I believe that if we carefully identify and cultivate
أنا مؤمن بأنه إذا حددنا ونَمَّيْنَا بحرص
the next generation of African leaders,
الجيل القادم من قادة أفريقيا،
then this generation four that is coming up
فإن هذا الجيل الرابع الذي بدأ بالبروز
will be the greatest generation that Africa
سيكون أعظم جيل شهدته أفريقيا
and indeed the entire world has ever seen.
بل والعالم أجمع.
Thank you.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.